Hello everyone.
How are you doing?
Welcome to CON42 Observability 2026,
and so excited to be presenting
this amazing topic with you.
My name is Emmanuella and I
am a cloud solution architect.
And in this section, I will be explaining
the very core importance of observability.
So I want you to sit tight while
watching this section, take your
pen and your writing pad, so you
would be able to put down every
important details from this section.
And also stay with me to the
very end, because you're going
to gain a lot from this section.
And with that being said, like I
said before, my name is Emmanuella
Okporom, and today we will be
talking about observability.
Okay?
So I chose the title for this
section, Beyond Dashboard.
And the reason is because dashboards
are very useful, but they don't
always tell the full story of
our platform or our website.
No, they don't.
Okay?
So in this section, I'm going to explain
observability from the beginner's
level, yes, using simple online
experience that we can relate with.
So if you're not an observability expert
or you've never come across this or
you've never heard the word observability
before, you don't need to worry.
Okay?
Like I said, you don't need to be an
expert to follow or to understand this
section, because I will be breaking
everything down in a beginner's level.
Okay?
And in this section as well, I
will be looking at or will be
covering what is observability.
What does this word mean?
Okay?
I would explain that to you.
So after this section, when you
hear of the word observability,
you know what it means in details.
Okay?
So I would explain what observability
mean and why it matters in
today's modern cloud system.
Okay?
And I will also explain how logs, metrics,
and traces can be used In observability,
how they help us to understand what is
actually going on in our system, what is
actually going on in our platform, what
is actually going on in our application.
Okay?
So by the end of this section, I want
you to have a simple idea that you can
get started with to configure your own
observability in your cloud platform.
Okay?
I want you to have a simple idea
that you can use in your own system
when designing your architecture.
Okay?
So that is the goal for
this particular session.
So like I said before, sit with me
in this section and trust me, you are
going to gain a lot from this section.
So with that being said, we are going to
dive right into today's section and get
to understand what this word observability
means and why it's very important.
Okay.
So let's begin with a simple example.
Okay?
Let's begin with a very simple example.
So imagine that you have an online
shopping website or an application, okay?
And when you open your observability
dashboard for your online shopping website
or application, everything looks amazing.
Everything looks good.
Your dashboards all looking green,
meaning your servers are running,
errors are low, your CPU looks amazing.
But in all of this looks, in all of
this fabulous dashboard looking all
correct and right, you got a call from a
customer or you got a customer complaint,
not just one, not two, not three.
You h- you got customers complain of being
able to make payments in your platform.
So what do you think that means?
Does it mean your observability
dashboard is actually wrong?
No.
It doesn't mean your
observability dashboard is wrong.
It doesn't mean your dashboard
is actually telling a lie.
No.
But in this particular scenario,
in this particular issue or this
particular atmosphere of, or your
clients or your customer being
unable to make payments, you kept
asking yourself, "What is happening?
I just checked my my platform
observability, and everything looks
good." Yes, everything looks good
because your dashboard is only showing
you what it was configured to show you.
It doesn't cover your
full customer experience.
Yes It is showing you what it was
configured to show you in your platform.
It is not showing you the full custom--
the full experience of your customer.
So the dashboards wouldn't work.
And now remember, the importance of the
business, the importance of observability
in our business, in our application
is not to show us all green dashboard.
Yes, that matters.
That's, that makes our mind be at ease
that our platform is actually running
correctly, our servers are running, our
CPUs are looking normal, low errors.
But what the business actually cares
more about is the customer experience.
So our dashboards have to tally
with our customer's experience.
The business doesn't want only
that the servers is running
okay or CPUs are looking normal.
It also cares about the customer can
make payments and complete an order.
The customers can carry out a
transaction in their platform.
That is what the business cares about.
So in this section, you see the
difference between what the dashboard
shows and what the customer experiences.
That is the core of this section.
That is where observability
becomes very important and that
is why this section is important.
So this section is going to let you
understand why your dashboard is
showing you something positive, all
green, servers are running perfectly,
low errors are low, CPU are normal.
But on the other side, the customers
are saying we can't carry out a
particular a, carry out a particular
transaction, task in your platform.
So that is why what we're
going to learn today.
Why the two of them needs to actually co-
well align to be able to ensure that you
know what is happening in your platform.
So let's quickly explain what we're
going to cover in that section, okay?
So the first thing we're going
to cover five different different
aspects in this section.
So the first thing we will be talking
about is what observability means.
What is observability?
The meaning of observability in
simple language, beginner level, okay?
So we will be covering the
meaning of observability.
What does it mean?
And then we will look at why modern cloud
systems can be difficult to understand.
Yes.
One action from a customer may pass
through many different systems.
So we are going to look at why
observability or why modern cloud systems
can be very difficult to understand
when it comes to observability, okay?
So the next thing we are going to
understand is we will talk about the
very important types or concept that
we need to know in observability.
We'll talk about logs, we will talk about
metrics, we will talk about trace, okay?
These are the three important
types of information that will
help us understand our system,
help us understand our application,
help us understand our platforms.
So we will be talking about the
evidence in observability, okay?
Which is what these three core
types concept is in observability.
And we will also look at how to include
observability in our architecture.
Yes.
So when designing architecture,
yes, we're looking at server, we're
looking at network, we're looking at
payment transaction, we're looking at
scalability, we're looking at security.
Observability needs to be included.
Observability is not an aftermath
Inclusion in the design?
No.
It has to be what we n- it has
to be a part of the design.
So you have to decide your observability
for that architecture, as well
as the scalability and security.
Okay?
So that is what we'll be covering today.
So we will look at how to include
observability when designing a
system, how to protect your sensitive
information, and how to manage costs.
Okay?
And finally, in this section I will
share simple checklist that you can use
to begin your observability journey.
Okay?
So this session isn't about telling you
which tool to buy or which tool to use.
It's about helping you to understand
the very important ideas that you
need to know about observability.
And trust me, if you stay to the
end of this section, I believe you
will be able to carry out your first
observability configuration in your
architecture or in your cloud platform.
Yes, because I will be sharing
the main ideas that you need for
that particular configuration.
Okay So now let's ask, what
exactly is observ- observability?
Yes.
So what is this particular
word, observability?
What does it mean in
the modern cloud space?
What does it mean in our application?
What does it mean in our website?
When we hear the word observability,
what are they talking about?
What does it mean?
Why is it important?
So in a simple word, I would say
observability is our ability to understand
what a system is doing by looking… By
the system giving us clues about what
is actually happening in our platform.
Okay?
Observability is having to understand
where, what, when is going on in
our application and our platform.
Okay?
That is what observability is.
It is simply understanding the where,
the when the what is going on at the back
end of our platform with our platform.
And this observability, it gives
us clues on what to look out for
when something breaks or when our
platform is encountering issues.
Okay?
So that is what observability means.
We don't need to think so big about it.
In simple, plain term,
that is what it means.
It's simply observing.
Okay?
And now observability needs to answer,
a good observability configuration
needs to answer three core questions.
Yes.
The first one is, what is
happening with my platform?
Okay, I own an application,
and I configure the
observability in my application.
That observability Should be
able to answer what is actually
happening with my platform.
Yes.
If it can't answer what is
happening in your platform,
then it is not observability.
So observability needs to answer what
is happening with our application.
Two, what's where is it happening?
Okay.
What location is this loss coming from?
What location are my clients
facing network issues?
What locations are my client
facing latency issues?
What location are my clients
facing scalability problem?
It should be able to tell you,
okay, what availability zone, what
location, where is it coming from.
So it should be able to give
you information of where in your
platform or your application.
And lastly, and the third one, it should
be tell, able to tell you why it happens.
Yes.
So your observability should
be able to tell you why.
It should be able to
answer the question why.
So the three core types of information
that observability should be able to
provide for you is, number one what is
happening with your application, where
it is happening, and why it happened.
Okay.
So these are the three very important
answers that observability should be
able to give any developer, anyone, okay,
that is working with that application.
So sometimes the problem may be…
Sometimes we might encounter some, a
challenge or a problem that we've, in our
application that we've never seen before.
Yes.
So the importance of observability in
a design is that a well-designed and
configured observability should be able
to give us clue, to be able to give the
engineers information to fix that issue.
If your observability doesn't give
the, the what, the where, and the why,
how will the developers be able to
figure out what is happening with our
platform and fix them early before it
even makes break the platform more.
Okay.
So a good well-designed system
always gives engineers enough
information to investigate issues.
Okay.
So observability is not just a
dashboard or is a particular tool.
No.
It is how we design a system so that
when something goes wrong, we can
find and fix the problem more quickly
than not having any clue at all.
So imagine you have a p- you have
a platform and you don't have any
observability configuration in that
platform, and you encounter an issue
with customer payments challenge.
Where do you even start from to start
figuring out what breaks, where it
breaks, why it breaks, what time?
It's very difficult, and this is
going to cost your business money.
So you see why observability is important.
So if you having a very good
observability configuration in your
platform, you can easily go to logs,
get to see logs, traces, your metrics.
With this information, your engineer
can fix the issue faster than not
having any observability set up at all.
So this is the core importance of
observability Now the question is,
are dashboard useful in observability?
Yes, they are.
Dashboards are very useful in
observability, but only if our
configuration when configuring our
observability, we bear in mind that our
dashboard only shows the information
that it was configured to show.
Okay?
The aspect of our platform
that it was configured to show.
So that is what dashboard shows.
So it is still important in observability.
So dashboard are very important.
It is very important, and they help us
see the important information quickly.
So for example, a dashboard may show
us how many requests are coming into
our platform and how many failed,
or whether the CPU is high or not.
Dashboard shows us this
information if we confi-configure
it to show us this information.
It shows us service availability,
the queue getting in and all of that.
It does show us.
But here is the limitation of a dashboard.
Every dashboards answers a question
that someone has selected in advance.
Every dashboards answers a question that
the engineer, the developer, whoever
is in charge of the observability of
the of that platform has selected.
That is the only thing that
the dashboard will show.
So let's say during a problem, we may
need to ask questions that the engineer
or the dashboard isn't selected to show.
Yes.
During problems, we may ask questions that
the dashboard wasn't designed to answer.
So when a problem happens and the
dashboard may not have the answers that
we need, this is because Our dashboard
configuration or our dashboard setup,
the information that we configure into
our observability dashboard is limited.
Yes, it's limited because we chose only
a particular aspect of the platform and
leaving the others vulnerable to CPU
high CPU or low server and all of that.
Okay?
So let me give another example.
So for example, it may show that
the total number of payments in our
online shop failed, but it may also
show that in a different availability
zone of this same mobile platform
of this same online platform,
customers are able to make payments.
Why do you think that happened?
Yes.
Remember the online platform that
we used in our first scenario that
customers were unable to make payments?
Yes.
So imagine customers in a particular
availability zone are facing payment
issues and other customers in a different
availability zones are able to pay.
But in our dashboard, we
only saw all green Why do you
think that is-- that happened?
That is because whoever configured
this online platform dashboard
didn't configure this dashboard to
show all the availability zone that
it is covering for its customers.
So you see why when configuring
your dashboard, what you select
for it to be visualizing your
dashboard is really important.
So a good observability gives us more
information to explore, to be able
to figure out these questions, to be
able to answer these questions when
it breaks or when incident occur.
Okay?
A dashboards are useful, but they cannot,
just on their own, they cannot show
us everything that we need to know.
Yes, dashboards are very important,
but just on their own, they can't show
us all we need to know in our system.
So s- this is where right
configuration comes in.
Yeah, okay?
This is where right
configuration comes in.
This is where monitoring and
observability have to work together.
Okay?
Yeah.
So monitoring and
observability work together.
They work hand in hand,
but they are not the same.
Okay?
So observability does a different
job, monitoring does a different job.
They are not the same,
but they work together.
So what is monitoring and what does it do?
Monitoring tells us that something is
actually something is wrong in our system.
So let me s- tell you.
Okay, let's give this example.
So for example, it's it may warn us
that- a payment error is occurring in
a part, a particular availability zone.
Yes.
It may warn us that more payments are
failing in a particular availability zone.
Okay?
That the system is becoming slow
in another availability zone.
Okay?
The-- It might tell us, monitoring
might tell us that network issue
is occurring in one part of our
customer's availability zone.
But monitoring may not
tell us why it happened.
Yes.
Monitoring may not tell
us why it happened.
So that is where observability comes in.
So observability help us to find the
cause of why network is failing in a
particular zone, why we're having payment
issue in a particular zone, why response
are slow in a particular zone, why the
queue is more full in a particular zone.
Observability help us to
answer the question why.
Okay?
It help us to find the cause.
What is the cause of this?
Why is it happening?
That is what observability does for us.
So it may show us that the payment
for customer A is slow because of this
reason and because of that reason.
Okay?
Because of a new update or
because a, a new release.
Observability does that for us.
Okay?
And now let's think of it like this.
Monitoring gives the alarm of
an issue in our platform, okay?
And observability gives us
the clue to fix that alarm.
It gives us the clue we need to fix that
alarm that observe-- that monitoring
has have brought to our attention.
So that is how they work hand in hand.
Okay?
So observability help us to know that an
issue or is occurring with our platform.
We have downtime or we have network issue,
we have slow response, and monitoring
help us to find the clue of why we have
slow response and why we have issue.
Okay?
This is how they work together.
So that is why we need both
monitoring and observability to
make our system run smoothly.
Okay?
So that is why we need monitoring
and we need observability.
Okay?
These two cannot be replaced because
they carry out two different important
jobs in monitoring and responding
fast to incidents with our platforms
So now imagine a customer may
see a website or an application
running smoothly, right?
But behind that application, there are
many services that are working together
to make that platform or that application
or the online shopping store that we're
using as a scenario work smoothly.
So many services.
So for example, when a customer click on
the payment button, one service takes the
order, another s- service processes the
payment transaction, and another service
saves the order, another service delivers
the successful payment transaction.
So you can see how current
modern cloud platforms work
with so many services, right?
Yes.
So this is, this may be running-- all of
the services may be running in different
places or managed by different teams.
Yes.
And if one service becomes slow
or crashes or fails The customer
may not be able to make payment.
And this is why I earlier on said
we will be looking at why it is
difficult to set up observability
in modern plat-- modern cloud.
Yes.
This is why modern cloud systems
can be very difficult to understand
because it operates with lot of
services which may not be even be
operating in one cloud platforms.
Yes.
These services might be in
different cloud platforms.
So that is why monitoring modern cloud
systems can be very difficult, and it
can be very difficult to understand.
So to find the problem, we need to
follow the customer's complaint journey.
We need to understand the
customer complaint journey.
We need to look at each service separately
so that we get to understand in detail
where the problem is coming from.
Okay?
Why we have slow payment
and why we're facing issues.
So when working with modern
cloud systems, monitoring is key.
So we need to monitor.
Imagine having different services
scattered all over different
platforms or by different teams.
Monitoring is key because monitoring
is what sets the alarm in motion
first before observability help us to
kn-know the exact location or the exact
service where the alarm is coming from.
Okay?
So you see why-- This is why
cloud modern cloud platforms, it's
difficult to understand because
of its scattered services, its
microservice kind of architecture.
Okay A small problem in
cloud ar-architecture could
actually travel so far.
Yes.
And the reason is because these
cloud architectures are built they…
First of all, they operate
with a lot of services.
A platform, a cloud, a, a platform that
is hosted in a cloud, that is cloud
native could be have so many services
that actually runs that platform.
And cloud architecture might be the…
A cloud architecture might be built
in a microservice kind of design.
So that is why once a
small problem occurs, it is
advisable to fix it very fast.
If not, it spread across
different service.
Okay?
So now, in a cloud system, one
small problem can affect other
parts of the of the service as well.
So using our same payment unable
to-- customer unable to pay make
payment in our online shop scenario.
So imagine that customer that was
unable to make payment just because they
want to truly purchase that item and
get a successful payment transaction,
they kept making same request.
And as they are making same
request, another customer is
still making same payment request.
So do you know what is
happening with our platform?
It grows.
This request, all of this request
that the customer is putting in, it
is going into our payment queue Or th-
therefore creating a very huge payment
queue for our backends to process,
which is another error on its own.
Yes, because so first of all, it was a
payment issue, and then now it has grown
to having lots of payment queues waiting
to actually be be successful, and this
is going to slow your platform down.
That is why it is difficult when
monitoring with modern clouds
architecture, modern cloud platforms
because of its scattered services.
And one platform might have their
payments in a different cloud provider
and have the other service in a different
cloud provider, and have the other
service in a different cloud provider.
Yes, it happens.
Okay?
So imagine not being able to cover
traces or logs for all of these services.
How do you then monitor it?
Okay.
So that is why in a cloud system,
one small problem can actually
affect the other systems if you
don't actually work on them faster.
So now let's say this problem occurs.
So let's say now we-- this payment
issue or this payment transaction
problem occurred, and we don't have
any observability in our platform.
How do we then get to trace- The issue.
How do we then get to find
clues to fix this issue?
Imagine her being in that scenario.
It's going to take ages.
Yes, and this ages is being
affected by your business.
Because customer not being able
to check out or make payments, it
means your business isn't moving, so
it's going to affect your business.
So that is why observability is very key.
It's very important.
But with observability, what the engineer
needs to look out for, the logs, the
metrics, and the traces using the metrics
ID, and they will be able to figure
out, "Oh, yeah, we are having queue.
We are having slowdown in our our
system because initially there was a
payment issue that have now affected
our payment transaction line." Okay?
So imagine this problem is occurring,
and the payment issue is only affecting
customer in availa- availability region
A, and the payment issue is not actually
affecting customer in a different region.
So it means even if the customer in a
different region payment is successful,
the processing time is going to take long
because of the multiple input of payment
that is occurring from availability zone
A. It's going to affect your business.
So that is why observability
is very important.
So with observability, we can connect
these incidents, this clues together,
and understand the full story of
what is happening with our platform.
So here is a simple way that I like
to think about observability, okay?
So imagine when we visit a doctor, okay?
The doctor doesn't just straight ahead
and say "This is what is wrong with you."
No, the doctor diagnose using a clue.
Yes.
The doctor asks questions
about our health.
about our temperature.
It has even asked question way
back on when was the last time this
occurred and that occurred, okay?
That is how I view
observability as well, okay?
So when a doctor is trying to
understand what is actually wrong with
the patient, the doctor doesn't just
normally use one piece of information.
No.
Okay?
The doctor use different information.
The patient's temperature, okay when was
the last time, dated back to what happened
to you or the symptoms and all of this.
All of this put together is a clue that
a doctor use to diagnose the patient.
Same it is with observability, okay?
So observability work the same exact way.
So metrics, it uses metrics to sh-
to show us the changes in numbers
that is occurring with our system.
It uses logs to give us detailed record of
events that is occurring in our platform.
And then it uses traces to show
us the journey of request that
actually occur with our platform.
These are all clues, okay?
So with this connection and
with this clue, it help us to
understand the cause of an issue
and to be able to fix the issue.
Okay?
So together, and observability
works with these three core
concept: traces, metrics, and logs.
Okay?
So in observability, there is
something called telemetry.
Okay?
So I don't want you to be scared.
Telemetry, oh, it's so technical.
No, it is not technical at all.
Okay?
So when you hear of the word
telemetry I don't want you
to think that it's technical.
No.
It sounds technical, but it doesn't
actually mean it is that technical.
So what is telemetry?
So telemetry is the information that a
system produce about what is actually
going on in our app- application.
It is the data, the information
that, that that is created by an
application containing traces,
information, logs, events of what
is going on in our application.
That is what is telemetry.
Okay?
So telemetry includes record of events,
yes, numbers showing the performance,
okay, of this application, and also
information showing how request
travels from one service to the other.
Telemetry gives us all
of this information.
Okay?
So telemetry shows us log, metrics,
traces, and how they are connected
together This is what is called telemetry.
So collecting a large amount of
telemetry doesn't automatically
give us a good observability.
No.
Collecting a large amount of data
doesn't give us a good observability.
So we may have millions record of
events, of logs, and still find
it difficult to answer a simple
question when our application breaks.
Okay?
So the information must be very useful.
The information that we're capturing
in our application must be very useful
and clear to help us solve an issue
with our application when it occurs.
Okay?
So the information should have things
like the name of the service, it
should be safe, it should have IDs.
All of these help us connect the dots.
Okay?
It help us to answer the question that
the team needs to carry out or to fix an
issue when it occurs with our platform.
But imagine having data without
an ID number, without the name of
the service that actually broke.
How would the team know?
So a good telemetry should contain
in- the right information, and
should also safeguard the details
of the clients, of the customers.
Okay?
A good data, a good telemetry should not
have sensitive information in it, but it
should give us a good enough information
to be able to fix and have clue of what
is happening with our applications.
Okay?
So let's start with logs.
Remember, I said a good telemetry
should be able to have logs,
metrics, and traces that help the
engineers to know the service, the
event, and the, and where it occurs.
This should able to provide the
answers to this question for the
engineers to be able to fix this this
issue with our application faster.
So now, what is logs?
What is a log?
A log is a system diary.
I call it as a system diary.
Okay?
It is it writes the record of what
is happening in our application.
Okay?
The event that is occurring in an
application, in a platform, even
a, a log keeps that in its diary.
Okay?
So for, for an example, one log could show
the pay-- could show where the payment
started from with the customer, could
show the first pay, the first customer
transaction or informations like that.
Another log could show the payment
service and why it did not respond.
Another log could show the third
party performance with that payment.
It could show if the third
party actually processed that
payment successfully or not.
So logs are useful when
the message are clear.
So it means the log message has to be
clear for the the engineer to understand.
Okay?
So a message that only says
something like, let's say something
went wrong, that does not give us
in… a good enough information.
Okay, something went wrong.
What time did it go wrong?
What is the name of the
something that went wrong?
Okay.
So a good log should tell us the name of
the service, Which service is this log?
Does which service have this log?
Okay.
You should be able to give us
the time, what happened, and
which request was affected.
That is a good log.
Okay?
And a log, like I said
previously, it has to be safe.
A log must always be safe.
The, the log should never contain
customer's information, password, details.
No, a log should be safe.
Never to contain customer's
personal information, password,
card details, sensitive information.
No, that shouldn't be included in a log.
Okay?
And the next one, we will
be talking about metrics.
What is a metrics?
What do you understand by metrics?
So metrics are numbers that show
how the system is performing.
It gives us the speed of the system.
It gives us the size, the changes
that occur in the systems.
Yes.
They are numbers that tells us
how our system is performing.
So metrics shows how many people
are using this service, how many p-
requests are actually failing, and
how many requests are going through,
how much memory is being used.
Metrics help us to notice changes quickly.
Yes, it help us to
n-notice changes quickly.
So let's give an example
using our payment as well.
Okay?
So imagine a payment fail Okay?
So a payment may fail many times at
one specific transaction or the other.
Okay?
So now let's say this payment
issue started few minutes ago,
and the metrics is capturing that
it is just one percent failure of
users that is facing this issue.
If the payment issue skyrockets to
a ten percent failure in payment or
a twenty percent, immediately our
metrics tells us this payment issue
is skyrocketing to this number.
Something is wrong with numbers.
It shows us what is wrong with numbers.
Okay?
So the metrics does not usually
tell us what is happening.
No.
Metrics does not usually tell us what
is happening, what is exactly happening.
Okay?
So but we can use traces and logs to find
out the cost of the spike in numbers,
of the error in numbers with payments.
That is where logs and traces comes in.
Metrics tells us the failure in numbers,
the percentage of which it's been
failed, it's been failing using numbers.
Then now to trace the call,
to trace the cause of it, we
use logs and logs and traces.
Okay?
So the number shows us the num--
The numbers of metrics shows us
the important part of the impact
that this particular payment
transaction is having on our system.
While logs and metrics shows us
the cost, the exact reason why
we're having this much impact
of payment error in our system.
Hope this is understood.
Now let's talk about trace.
What is a trace?
Okay, we've talked about logs,
we've talked about metrics,
so let's talk about trace.
What is a trace?
A trace help us to follow one
customer's transaction, one com--
customer's action, one customer's
task through from beginning to end.
Traces, trace help us to s- to, to
keep keep steps on what is happening.
Once a customer clicks a request
or once a customer carries out a
transaction, it follows through what is
happening till response is given back.
Or if response fail, then we can
identify why it failed using trace ID.
Okay?
So for example, using the
same customer payment issue.
Okay?
So once, when our customer click
paid, the request move through
different services that is connected
to that payment transaction.
Okay?
So one part check the order the
order process, the payment linking to
third party service and the result.
Okay?
So if anything occur with our
payment, the best place to see
where it failed, okay, is trace.
Because trace shows us each step that
transaction has actually carried out.
Okay?
And these steps are called span.
So it shows us the span of
what have actually occurred.
If the transaction was successful,
if it wasn't successful, it shows us
which of the step took longer time
for it to deliver and where it failed.
Okay?
So it also shows us how logs…
It also shows us the the, it also
showed us how long the payment
took or how long a task took.
Okay?
It shows us the duration.
So let's say previously, from our
previous observability, it takes client
one minute to carry out a transaction.
And now we're seeing or when we're
doing our diagnosis to fix the payment
issue, we're seeing that in the API
call, which was usually taking one
minute, it's now taking three minutes.
Now we know, okay, fine, the
slow, the s- the payment being
slow, it's connected to the API.
Or let's say in the third party
connection, which is the third party
connection, payment connection,
initially it used to take two minutes
or two seconds, and now it is taking
five seconds So now we're-- we've--
a tra-trace has enabled us to
identify that the, the problem has
to do with third-party connection,
third-party integration, right?
So this help engineers to be able
to find and fix errors faster.
So instead of scrambling all of
the application trying to figure
out, oh, where did it occur?
Why did it occur?
When did it occur?
We use log, metrics, and traces
to be able to get the clue of what
happened and build a, a full story
of what happened and then know where
the cause is and where to fix it.
Okay?
So together, these three
concept, these three types of
information makes up observability.
Yes.
So these three types of
information makes up observability.
So with logs, metrics, and traces,
they are very useful for engineers
to connect the dots of what is
actually going on in a system.
Okay?
So we can't do without using
trace ID to locate where an
event occur and why it occurs.
No.
So now trace ID.
Think of trace ID tracking a number, okay?
Tracking a number in your system.
So each user request has
its own unique own ID, okay?
And once a customer clicks on a task or
a transaction, this ID follows through.
Okay?
That is why you see when a customer
have an issue, it's easy to trace
because there's an ID attached to it.
So imagine an ID isn't attached
to every API call that goes on.
How is it being traced?
So this trace ID help us to locate
the actual customer that faced the
error and where the error occurred.
Okay?
So now let me give an example.
For an example, a metrics may show that
the payment failed and have increased.
Yes.
Remember I said, metrics give us
the numbers of incidents occurred.
So a metrics may show that a payment
fail or it has increased, but a metrics
wouldn't tell us where it failed.
Okay?
So for an engineer to be able to
know where this payment failed,
okay, an engineer use the trace ID.
So with the trace ID, an engineer can
find where the payment actually failed.
An engineer can see the
cause of the payment failure.
With the trace ID.
So that is the importance of trace ID.
Without a shared ID, it may take longer,
or it may be difficult for an engineer
to actually get to see and know the
exact service of this payment failure.
But with a trace ID, it is easy to
pinpoint and know where and what
is affecting the payment issue.
Okay?
So connecting the information and
giving… It can help the, the engineers
connect information and give them detailed
information on the path to fix the errors.
So that is the importance of trace ID.
Okay?
Without trace ID, it is very difficult.
And every customer transaction,
every customer task, every customer
request have a uni-a unique trace ID.
Okay?
So having looked at metrics, logs,
and traces, okay, now let's follow
the full customer's customer journey.
The customer click on the
Pay Now in our platform.
Okay?
The API receives this order.
Now, the payment provides
the process for the payment.
Okay?
The database save the
results for the payment.
The f- the, the… And finally, the
customer receives a confirmation
once the payment goes through.
So every part of this journey matters.
Every part of this
payment journey matters.
And do you know why?
Sometimes a technical request
can appear successfully while
the customer real result fails.
Yes.
Sometimes it's, it, it-- the payment
request could show successfully, but the
c-customer real result actually fail.
So for example, the payment may
successfully go through, but the order
configu- the order confirmation may never
be created as well by the third party.
So if we only monitor the payment
request, imagine we only monitor
the payment request, we may think
everything worked properly because
the payment shows successfully, right?
But what about the
payment cost confirmation?
What about the payment confirmation?
So a good observability have to-- A
good observability must not overlook
or a good observability must configure
to monitor every aspect of the service.
Okay?
Every aspect of the service
without leaving anyone untraced.
Good observability should also record
important business results, okay?
Such as payment acceptance,
orders saved confirmation.
It should be able to cover m-if every
aspect of the service because imagine
your observability covers your payment
transaction, but not the confirmation
of the payment or not the confirmation
of your order even being released
to the customer How would you know?
You wouldn't know because your
observability only covers a
particular aspect of what is
happening in your application.
Okay?
So a good observability n- it
needs to cover an important, a very
important aspect of your application.
And this helps because it shows
whether the customer actually
carried out this transaction or not.
It shows whether the transaction
was successful or not.
It shows whether a tax… Now,
let's leave the transaction apart.
It knows, it shows whether a tax
actually goes through or not.
It shows detail detail observability
information to help engineer
fix an issue without leaving
lapses in your observability.
Okay?
So a good observability should
be able to cover every crook
and cranny of your application.
It should be able to cover the important
services, important parts of your
application without leaving any loop So
having known what is observability and the
types of, or the concept or things that
we need to look out for in observability,
which are metrics, traces, and logs.
Now, we're going to go into
choosing observability, the right
tool for your observability.
So before you go ahead and jump
into choosing a tool for o-your
observability, yeah, you first need
to consider first the user's journey.
Okay?
What should the user be
able to do in my platform?
You have to consider that.
So in our payment example, yeah, what
the business wants the user to be
able to do is to be able to shop Pay
successfully and have a cons successful
payment and a successful checkout.
These are the things that we wanted
the, the user to be able to do
in our online payment platform.
Okay?
So this we have to consider, user journey.
And the next thing is to
decide how to measure this.
We have to decide how do we measure,
how do we ensure that the user's
journey is actually successful?
Okay.
How do we measure that what the
user is experiencing is what
we can see and relate with?
Is what, it's what our
observ-observability is showing us.
Okay?
So we can measure how many
customers complete their payment
successfully and how long it takes.
Okay?
That might be what we want
for our online platform.
And then we choose the target for the
level of service that we want to provide
or configure in our observability.
Okay?
And the reason for this, that it helps
us to be able to ensure that we're
configuring the right service and
the right area in our application for
our observability in our platform.
So it ensures that we're not
overlooking the important part of
what our business needs to run.
Okay?
So it's just like the business
needs for A, Y, Z to be functional
for us to have for that is what
a successful platform is for us.
But our observability is showing
F, B E, which is something
different, so how do we monitor it?
Okay?
So before choosing any tool, first
we have to consider the user's
journey, useful measurements.
So what are we using to measure
against customers' experience?
And the targets, which services are
we targeting to monitor, to observe?
Okay?
So these are the things that
we need to consider before even
choosing an observability tool.
We have to bear this in mind, okay?
And to be able to carry out this,
we have to consider certain concepts
in targets, in customer customer
experience measurements, and all of that.
So the first thing that we need to
look out for- before choosing a tool
is we need to understand the service
level indication that we want.
Okay?
So it's also known as XLI.
Yes.
And it stands for
service level indication.
Okay?
So what is service level indication?
So in plain English, a, it is a
number that tells us how the service
or how our perform-- our platform
is performing for the users.
Yes.
It, for example, it gives us, it tells
us information about successful checkout,
failed checkout, complete orders, valid
checkout attempts, and all of that.
So it's gives us information about
how the service in our application
is actually performing for users.
That is what is an XLI.
Okay?
So now The important thing is that it help
us to measure the customer's experience.
So a CPU, okay, a server
cares about the platform.
It shows us information
about the platform.
Server is running on the platform,
is doing well, is running perfectly.
CPU usage CPU usage for
your pl-platform, it's okay.
It's running perfectly.
These are platform informations.
Okay?
So what a good SLI measures
the customer's service.
It measures the customer's experience.
Okay?
It gives us information about service
as as aligns with what the customer
can actually carry out in our platform.
Okay?
So this is one concept, or this is
one information that we need to bear
in mind, or we need to look out for
before choosing any observability tool.
So we have to check up what is the
service level indication that we want
for this platform, for this application.
Okay?
And the next is service level objective.
Yes.
So service level objective in a plain
language, it's it targets what we want
the service of our application to meet.
Okay?
Service level objective is simply the
target that we've set for our application.
Unlike service level indication, which
is measuring the customer's experience.
Okay?
And XLO, which is how it is also
known, is showing the target of what
we want to reach in our application.
Okay?
The target we want the service to meet.
That is what XO- SLO means.
So now let me give an example of SLO.
So imagine that our SLO may be to
say, let's say nine- ninety-nine point
nine percentage of checkout attempt.
That is what we want
to achieve in a month.
Okay?
So this means that out of, let's
say, out of a hundred or a two
hundred people that visited our
site, we want at least ninety-nine
percent of successful checkout.
That is the target that
we have for that platform.
Okay?
That is what is a service level objective.
So service level objective simply means
is the target that we're setting to reach
for a particular service in our platform.
Okay?
So this, th-this, This only explains what
the business targets for our platform is.
Okay?
So why service level indication
measures the customer's experience.
Okay?
So that is the difference.
Service level indication it's
more of what's the customer
experience with our platform.
Okay?
Why service level objective is the
target that we've set for our service,
our platform to be able to meet.
Okay.
So a simple way to monitor a service.
A simple way to monitor a service
is to watch out for four core
important signs in our platform,
in our application, in our service.
Okay?
And these are called four golden signs.
Yes.
They are called four, four golden signs
because they are really important.
The first one is latency.
So what is latency?
Latency is simply how long
does it take for a transaction
to go on, to be completed?
How long does it take for a content
to be delivered to its user?
Simply how long.
Okay?
This means how long the
service took to respond.
Okay?
That is what is latency.
And the target of majority of your site
should be to have low latency, okay?
To have low latency, to deliver
content to your users fast.
That should be the target of your
application, okay, of your platform.
So the second thing we'll
be talking about is traffic.
So what is traffic?
Traffic simply means
how much work arrived.
Okay?
Traffic simply means how much
work is going into the system.
Traffic simply means how many
users are coming into our platform
That is what traffic means.
And the goal of a good platform is to
be able to accommodate, to be able to
still stand firm regardless of any plat-
any regardless of the amount of traffic
that is coming into your platform.
That is the goal.
That is a good application
or a good platform.
A good platform should be able to scale
and meet up with traffic demand, okay?
And scale down when there is no traffic.
That is a good platform architecture.
That is a good platform, okay?
Regardless of the amount of traffic
that is coming into your platform should
be able to withstand and carry out
transactions as it should, regardless
of the platform or of the, the traffic.
And the third one is errors.
Yes.
This tells us how much work is
failing in our system, okay?
Errors simply tells us how much
work is failing in our system.
How much work failed in a transaction.
How much work failed when a client
or a customer carried out a task.
And the fourth thing, the fourth
golden sign that we need to
look out for is, If saturation.
Yes.
So what is saturation?
This simply means how close
a system is to its limits.
So for example, the system may be
running out of memory or have too
many requests coming in and waiting.
Okay?
So these four signs, these four golden
signs help us to see when something is
actually changing in our platform, when
something is changing in our application.
Okay?
So we can then use traces, logs, and
metrics to be able to fix, to find out, to
be able to find out what is failing, why
it is failing, and get them fixed before
it creates more harm to our platforms.
Okay?
So let me note something.
Not every changes, not every
change in your observability
dashboard is an emergency.
No.
Not every change is an emergency.
Okay?
So for instance, your CPU usage may
increase while service is still,
while your service is still running
normally, while customers are still
able to process with payments.
Yes.
So an alert should be when a customer
says, "I can't make payments."
Yes.
An alert is when s-something breaks
and it affects your platform.
Okay?
An alert is when someone's attention is
needed to carry out an action to fix that
issue, or when customers are affected by
an incident or a break in your platform.
Okay?
That is where an alert comes in.
But not every chart, dashboard issue
is actually affecting your platform.
Okay?
Because most times CPU might be running
perfectly, CPU might CPU might be
having increase, there might be increase
in your application CPU, but your
platform is really working perfectly.
Okay?
So if your team receive many,
let's say, many unimportant alerts,
people may begin to ignore them.
Yes.
They could even be mistaken
for serious problem.
Yes.
But a useful alert that your team needs
to really check as soon as possible Is the
one that affects your customer's usage.
Is the one that affects your transaction.
Is the one that affects tax.
Your customers being unable to carry
out transaction or request in your
platform, that is an, that is a a,
an alert trigger that your engineers
need to move fast into action and
fix before it breaks more services.
So let me give an example.
It could be the team or the customer
couldn't complete a checkout.
Yes.
That is a very important alert.
Okay?
So dashboard could show generally
ch- general changes, but an alert
should show clear, explained, detailed
transaction information that failed.
Okay?
An alert should clearly explain why
Someone needs to actually act fast.
An alert to-- should clearly
explain a problem that is
affecting your platform, okay?
And that is when your engineers
should spring into action.
That is an alert that
needs to be fixed fast.
Okay?
So when an engineer is trying to fix or
trying to or trying to know the cause
of an incident in your platform, okay?
Without the correct information and
connected information that gives clue
to the engineer to know where to look
out for, the engineer can spend a lot
of time trying to rebuild and figure
out the problem, trying to get the
incident, trying to figure out what
actually went wrong in the platform.
Yes.
So they may open several dashboards.
They may open several services, searching
through logs, using different times and
checking recent release and contacts
different teams just to fix an, an,
an incident that has occurred because
they don't have the right information.
Because they don't have the right
clue that could tell them this
is exactly what is happening.
This is the full story, okay?
Because they don't have the right
connected information to give them
the, the clue that they need to
solve that particular incident.
So with this, without having connected
information, detailed information, a
large part of the engineer's investigation
becomes searching up and down and
guessing where the problem may occur
or where the problem occurred, okay?
But with a good observability,
the investigation, the engineer
investigation becomes begins
with the, the customer problems.
It begins with the right place
where the, the issue actually
occurred because the engineer have
a lot of information to go by with.
So the engineer sees the affected metrics,
then open the traces, view the logs,
and gets connected information of step
to step on how everything occurred.
This makes an engineer
fix fix issues faster.
Okay?
Now, at this time, the engineer can
also check which version of the services
was running before the issue occur.
This is what observability does.
Okay?
So observability does not
make every incident easy.
But guess what it does?
It removes unnecessary searching,
guessing, and gives the team a
shorter path From the customer's
problem to a useful action.
Observability doesn't hundred
percent solve every issue in your
platform, in your system, no.
But it does one thing right.
It gives your engineers the right clue to
know what occurred and at what time, okay?
Instead of leaving them guessing.
So that is what observability does.
It gives the right clue and help
them connect the dots to be able
to fix the issue at the right time.
So remember I said observability should
be included in your architecture.
Yes, it shouldn't be an afterwards
event or afterwards process, no.
Obs- an observability should be included
in your arch- in your architecture.
Observability should be
included in the architecture
of your design, of your system.
Yes.
So first, application and services
provide logs and metrics and and traces.
Instrumentation adds useful information
such as the service, the name, the
version, the ID, and the timing, okay?
So a collector can then receive all of
these metrics or all of these, Okay.
Now, let's say our collector
receives the information, okay?
Organizes this information and send
it to the tool that my team use, the
tool that the company observability--
the, the company engineer use
for their observability, right?
The team then takes this search logs,
view traces, and create dashboard, and
receives alerts using this information
that have been built in our collection.
Yes, that is done.
But that's-- but collecting just
that information and displaying it is
not the final goal of observability.
No.
The, the team must use that information
to find a problem that is affecting
the platform or a problem that is
the platform is indicating an error
before it breaks the platform.
That is the essence of taking those
metrics, those logs, and those traces.
It's not just taking them
to build a dashboard.
No.
The team have to use them to find
problems in our application, in our
system, in our platform, and fix those
problem before they break the platform.
Fix those problem before
it affects customers.
Use those clues to trace what is
actually not right, what is not actually
functioning right with our platform.
Okay?
And that is what the team should do.
And OpenTelemetry gives us or gives the
team a common way to collect information,
to collect data, okay, without being
tied to one platform OpenTelemetry
gives the engineer options, okay?
Without being tied to using one
platform observability tool.
So that is what OpenTelemetry
does for us, okay?
So when trying to get clue of what is
actually occurring or what happens or
what is happening to a system, the most
useful information comes from the points
of movement, the steps that occur in a
customer's or a user target or or request.
Okay?
So the most information comes from
the point of where the work moved
from the, to what service it moved to
and the different steps it occurred.
That is, if that is the very useful
information when trying to get a clue.
Okay?
So now let's give an example.
So for example, when, for
example, your application or your
service, okay, a customer goes
there and send a payment request.
Okay?
Or the payment service save the
customer's information in your database.
Okay?
But at the end of the customer
handing over or at the end of the
customer finish purchasing in your
platform, okay, it took longer for
payments to actually go through.
Yes.
So it's, it could be the payment was
successful or the payment failed.
It actually took longer For
it to actually go through.
Okay?
So where are we going to see this trace?
We're going to see it in the different
steps and the particular information or
the particular concept in observability
that provides this, this particular
information for us is the trace, remember.
Is the trace because trace follows
the customer's input, the customer
transaction, the customer's pa-- the
customer's task from be- end to end.
Okay?
So trace is what is going to record the
customer's end-to-end transaction or input
and gives us a detailed information with
an ID to be able to trace why the payment
actually took long in the first place.
Even if it was successful, why did
it take long for it to be successful?
Okay?
So imagine your customers are having
delayed payments, even if it might be
successful, but they say it takes longer.
So with trace ID, you could be
able to tell which service, which
steps in our payment our payment
process made this took longer.
So that is what trace does for us.
Okay?
And one thing is that automatic
observability tool, right?
They record many technical steps for
us, but they don't always understand
what is important to our platform.
What is the service level
indication or what is the service
level objective that we've set.
Okay?
This is where the team must decide
which customer action and results
to be recorded in the observability.
Remember I talked about this before?
Yes, this Open Telemetry and other
automated tool, they provide data.
They gather this data for us, but they
don't know which important aspects or
which aspect is important to our business.
So that is why the team must take this
data and configure the observability and
the alert to ensure that it pinpoints the
area of the business that is key And the
reason is because this data that we get
from the tool, from the automatic tools or
observability tools, gives us information,
but they don't give us how to use it.
So now it is left for your observability
department, your engineer, to take
this information and configure the
right alerts for your platform.
Okay?
Bearing in mind the core areas or
the core services that the business
wants to look out for to ensure that
it doesn't crash the business, to
ensure that customer experience is
still going as smooth as possible.
Okay?
And when collecting information, okay,
when gathering logs and all event
logs and all, we must be very careful
about the information we collect.
Okay?
Logs and other telemetries are
accidentally… might accidentally
contain customer client information.
Yes.
Password, it could be password,
it could be card information,
sensitive informations.
These are not to be in our logs.
Okay?
So when gathering information, we have to
be very careful that our logs information
does not contain password, secret
key payment details, and a lot more.
Okay?
Email address, phone numbers, customer ID.
No, those are to be protected
and not to be in our logs.
They are to be protected
So please, your log should
never ever have these details.
It is risky.
So instead of, instead we can
record safe information in our
observability, such as service name.
Yes.
Recording a service name in
our observability help us to
know which service is actually
does this incident occur.
Yes.
So it help us to know the exact
service for us to look out
for when an incident occur.
Okay?
Another thing is could be the application
version, application location, the results
ID, transaction ID, and all of that.
So these are the information,
time and location.
These are the information that could,
that should be in our logs because these
are the information that we need to be
able to trace and get a clue of the full
story that, that might occur when service
breaks or when a comp-- customer complain
about anything or when monitoring.
Okay?
But never ever should you include any
sensitive information in your logs.
No, that is not best practice.
Okay?
So the collector can also move
or hide private information
before it can be stored.
Yes.
So you can set your collector
to remove or hide private
information before it is stored.
Okay?
Collecting more information is not
always better the importance or the
important information should be useful
and safe and should be an information
that gives you clue to solve an incident,
not just collecting random information.
Yes.
Okay?
It should be an information that is
clear, useful, that leads you to solve
a problem, not just random information.
And never customers' bank details
or sensitive information to be
included in your data collection.
It is not best practice But
we should also know that
observability costs a lot of money.
Yes.
Okay?
So a busy system can create a huge
amount of logs, metrics, traces,
and storing all of this information
forever can become very expensive
because of course, yes, you…
storage, database, it could takes, it
could take a lot of money to store this
information in a storage in a storage
service for a long time or forever.
Okay?
But if we decide to delete some
information that is not necessary or
take in information, only the important
informations, then it saves us money.
Okay?
We may have the information
we need to solve a problem.
That saves us money.
Instead of randomly just gathering
informations of different service
and different platform that
might not even give us clue.
So you should know that when setting your
collection, okay, your collection tool,
you should consider payments, and you
should consider, "Is this information
that I am scraping, is it necessary?
Is it necessary or is it going to
l- be able to give me a clue when
an incident occur or to be able to
monitor the system and ensure that my
system w- always runs perfectly?" Okay?
So we need to keep the most
useful information only.
Yes, we need to keep the
most useful information only.
So this may include errors.
Yes, this may include error logs.
It could, it may include low
requests on on useful customer
journey and information from a new
application update and a lot of that.
Okay?
So for n- for a normal and a
repeated request, we can keep only
a small number of example, okay,
to save us paying more on data.
So this… I think this
is called sampling.
Yes.
So for a repeated request, we can
keep a small number of data to be able
to analyze and monitor the system.
Okay?
That is helpful instead of taking
repeated same data over and over again.
And we can also keep a s- a, we can also
keep some informations for a shorter time.
So let's say we decide to monitor
our system against new release Okay?
A new release of a particular service.
So we could decide to take logs,
metrics, and traces for users
to get users' request events and
all of that in that new release.
But once we're done monitoring and
analyzing and getting the result
we want for our new release,
we could go ahead to delete it.
So this help us to save money.
Yes.
Because keeping those information
for a long time, you are going
to be paying for storage.
Okay?
So this help us to save money when
it comes to observability and help us
to choose the right information that
we need for our system and business
to be able to function properly.
Okay?
And give us clue on what we should look
out for instead of just paying randomly
for informations that are not useful
So some of most useful information
of our observ- observability or our
collection comes from the point where,
Metrics moves like one, the steps.
It comes from understanding the steps
that goes on in each of the customer's
tasks or customer requests, okay?
That is where most of the information,
important information comes from.
From the point where the customer clicks
the button, the steps which occurs
before the transaction is completed.
And that information is
given to us by trace, right?
So the trace help us to understand the
end-to-end transaction of a customer
or the end-to-end task of a customer.
So this is where an important information
comes from that help us to understand
and give us clue when trying to solve
a, our platform errors or trying to
figure out what is happening, why
an incident occur at war, or why
customers are unable to make payments.
Okay?
At… we could record the
final business results.
So let's say using our our
payment transaction story.
So now we could decide to record
the final customer's payments, be
it successful or not successful.
Traces help us to understand how
many client transaction actually went
through, how many was successful,
how many was delayed, at which
point of which it was delayed.
Okay?
Traces help us.
And now in this time and in this
era, we might have automatic some
collection tools that help us to scrape
and collect datas from our platform.
But this tool does not help
us understand how to use this
data that is being collected.
Yes.
This tool does not help us to understand
what is important to our customer.
The team, your observability team, your
engineering team, have to be the one
to decide, in all of this data that
we've taken, in all of these traces
that we've scraped, which is most
important to set an alarm to monitor,
to ensure that our customer gets the
best out of our platform, to ensure
that nothing breaks in our platform.
Yes, it is okay to gather datas, to gather
metrics, to gather logs, to gather to
gather events, requests of customers.
But your observability team needs
to know what to look out for, needs
to understand your business, your
platform service level indication,
your platform service level objectives.
This help them make the right
decision To use the right data,
to scrape and collect the right
information using your collector tools.
Okay?
And when collecting data, when using
our collector tool to collect datas
and metrics from our platform to
understand what is going on, we have
to be very careful to ensure that
we're taking the right information.
Okay?
We have to be very careful to ensure
that the informations-- about the
informations we're collecting.
Okay?
We have to ensure that logs and other
telemetry can can not accidentally
contain customers' private information,
customers' sensitive information.
No, that should not be included
in our event logs or in traces.
Not at all.
We-- our logs must not contain
passwords secret keys payment
details, email address, IDs and all.
No.
That should not be included in our logs.
Okay?
So instead, we should record, our
logs should have information that
can help us to analyze a clue of
an event or be able to visualize
what is going on in our platform.
And what is the information that
our log event needs to get to have?
Our log record should have information
such as the service name, time, location,
version, and general informations
on… that will help us get clue on
incidents and also understand what
is going on our, in our platform.
But never should it contain
customer sensitive information.
No password, no credit detail, no
email ID, none of that, and many
other sensitive information should
not be included in your logs.
Okay?
Your team should agree upon the safety
rules when co- when collecting datas.
Okay?
The safety rules when collecting datas.
What should go into your data log?
Your observability team, your
company should agree upon that.
Okay?
The collector, your collector tool can
can be set and configured to remove
customer sensitive to or hide them even
before you get to store your information.
Yes.
So you should configure your collector
tool to be able to hide customer sensitive
information, remove them totally before
you get to save your your script or
before you get to save the information.
Okay?
So collecting more information
is not always the best.
Yes.
The information that you are collecting
should be only the information that
you need to monitor your platform, you
need to get clue and fix issues and
not customer sensitive information.
Okay?
The information should be useful, safe,
and the collector or the collection of
the, the information should be clean.
Okay?
It should be clean.
When clean, it means it should not
contain any customer's information.
So you need to configure your collector
tool to ensure that it doesn't contain
any customer sensitive information
before you save those information.
Okay?
Now, one thing I know, yes, I
know I've said about a lot about-
Getting data and all of that.
But one thing you should bear
in mind is observability on
its own costs a lot of money.
Yes.
It costs a lot of money because
you collect datas, right?
Datas are being collected
and saved, right?
So imagine you taking millions
of data and saving them forever.
So your company will keep
spending a lot on data storage.
Okay?
So instead of spending a lot on
data storage, why don't you use
only the data that is necessary,
that is needed for your platform?
Don't store repeated data.
So if you notice repeated requests,
pattern is coming in, so you take only
one of that request and save it, and don't
keep taking the same repeated request.
Okay?
And again, for instance, if you are
setting a collection or observability for
you to be able to monitor a new release
in your application, once you monitor
the new release devis-- and get the
results you want, you delete that data.
If the data is no longer
needed, you just delete it.
This saves you money.
Instead of storing information, storing
datas that at the den- end of the
day, your observability tools and your
company don't even get to use them.
Yes.
If you don't want to totally delete the
data because you think that you might need
them in future, okay, then you can archive
these datas because it saves you more.
Archiving the data saves you
more than storing the data in the
present time or storing the data
that you can easily retrieve.
Okay?
So data storage is, costs a lot of money.
So if you gather datas, gather only the
data or the information that you need
to g- that you need to fix an issue
in your platform, that you need to get
clue when carrying out an incident fix.
Okay?
Don't just scrape or get random
data using your collector tool.
No.
Okay?
Take datas that are useful
for your platform, for your
organization, and when you're done
with temporary data, delete them.
Okay?
If you are also not using data
frequently, particular logs, metrics,
or traces frequently, you can archive
them if you don't want to delete them.
This saves your company money.
Okay?
So now let's get to understand how is
logs, metrics, and traces being sent.
How are they collected and sent?
So the telemetric pipeline Is the
part that collects this information
and send the platform or the
application logs, metrics, and traces.
Yes.
So the telemetry pa- pipeline is the part
that collects all of this and send it.
Okay?
The system can also have problems.
For example, your collector, our collector
may receive too much information.
Yes.
It may receive too much information
that the connection may fail.
Sometimes data may even
be delayed or lost.
Yes, it happens.
So because when you're
taking informations, you're
taking tons of information.
So if your collector can't handle that
ton of information, you could have
data delay, you could have failure,
and you could have loss of data.
The collector too is a software as well.
Yes.
So it could fail.
That is why we also need to check
out our observability information.
Yes.
To check out our observability information
is being collected cor-correctly.
We have to check our
observability information
to es-ensure that it's not
failing, it's not delayed.
Yes.
To ensure that our collector
too is working as it should.
Okay?
So a problem with a telemetry should never
stop the main application from running.
It shouldn't stop your problem,
your platform from running.
Okay?
So if a telemetry service fails,
customer should still be able to make
payments, should still be able to
carry out transactions, should still
be able to carry out requests and
complete this request successfully.
Okay?
So your team, my team should decide which
information can wait, which information is
important, which information can we drop,
and which information, impose a problem
if we don't get information in that area.
Okay?
Which problem needs an alert?
Yes.
Which problem it's it's important
for us to actually collect data from?
Is which problem or which service
is important for the business,
for the platform to gather
metrics and observability and get
an alert when an issue occurs?
So your team should be
able to decide this.
Yes.
So randomly just configuring your
observability for all the service in your
platform doesn't make it work because you
might be overlooking the main business or
the main business logic of your platform.
Yes, you might be overlooking the
core services that your platform,
that your business needs to run.
So your team needs to take
into consideration what
is promised to our users.
What is the user journey?
What should we fulfill for our users?
So now, in the case of our online
platform, the important core value and
what we want for our plat- platform is
the journey, the experience we've promised
our users is to p- we promise them that
they can be able to shop on our platform,
check out from our platform, pay success
in their platform, and get payment
configuration and check out successfully.
This is what we have
promised our customers.
So in this case, in this
scenario, our observability have
to be configured around this.
Okay?
Ensuring that we get alerts when
an issue occur with any of the
services because that is what
we have promised our customer.
And observability isn't just
randomly configuring and
checking your whole platform, no.
Observability is to ensure that the
business stays in line with what
has been promised to the customer to
ensure your platform is running, I
could use the word twenty-four seven,
without having customer complain.
That is the core reason of
observability So with that being
said, observability should begin
before an application is released.
Yes, when designing your platform, okay?
So during planning, choose the important
customer journey and decide what the
team needs to understand about it, okay?
During your development and during the
development, add the useful logs, metrics,
and traces that should be able to get
all of the detailed data that is needed
for you to monitor your platform and
even be able to get close and fix issue
before it's, before it escalates, okay?
Now, during testing, okay?
During testing, create a small problem.
Yes.
This will help you know or this,
this small problem will, will--
it will not be harmful to your
platform or to your customer.
But what it's going to do is like
triggering or is like creating a
problem and then monitoring your
observability configuration if it
actually triggers in the right direction.
Okay?
So during testing, create a small problem
and then check whether the metric shows
the problem, check whether the traces
shows where it happens, and check what
the logs explain, okay, that happens.
Th-this is why testing
is also important, okay?
So after the application goes live,
okay, alerts should be focused on the
problem that affects the customers.
I can't stress this enough, okay?
After your application goes live,
your observability configuration
should be focused on the problem, the
services that affects the customer.
This is what it should focus on.
Your alerts should be focused on the
problem that affects your customer.
Okay?
When an incident happen, the team
should use what is, what it learns
or what is important to them,
okay, to fix the application.
Okay?
So when an incident happens, the team
should use what it- Like the the traces,
the test results the log events, the
metrics, they should use this information
to be able to fix the event faster.
That is what-- That is the essence
of gathering this information.
Okay?
So this help them to fix event faster
and also learn while fixing this event.
Okay?
It help them to learn to
improve your platform.
So let's say for ins-instance,
using our payments issue or using
our customer payment scenario.
If the co- the, your observability team
or your engineering team gets to fix your,
fix this problem, they've learned from it.
They are going to see why the problem
occur, when it occurs, and then
fix your platform so this problem
doesn't occur, may not occur again.
Or even if it may occur again, it's not
going to be as severe as the previous one.
Okay?
So every incident should make
the system easier to understand
next time an incident occurs.
Yes.
So every incident should make
the system, your platform, your
application easier to understand
the next time an incident occur.
That is the essence of tr- logs, event,
traces, alert, and observability.
When it comes to setting the right
observability for your platform, for
your application, trust me, you do
not need to change everything at once.
No.
Start with the important customer action.
Start with the important customer
journey or customer experience
that you really want to keep.
Yes.
Such as making payments, such as
carrying out transaction effectively.
Start from there and configure
the right alerts for that service.
Okay?
What you need to do is to decide what
success results should look like.
Yes.
What should success
results should look like?
How would you measure it?
Remember we talked about service level
indication and service level objective?
Yes.
How are you measuring your targets?
What success looks like?
Okay?
And You go, you're going to use this
metrics, this indication and metrics
to configure your alerts so that you
get to meet up with your service level
indication, your customer experience.
Once a customer clicks, you get to
understand what goes on and your target.
If you're setting a successful, a
success rate for a 1,000 payment
checkout in a month, then this
target have to align with your alert.
Okay?
Together with a, a, a great configuration
and information observability alerts,
you will be able to meet up with your
service level objective and service
level indication target that you have set
for your business or for your platform.
Okay?
Another thing is you need to make
sure that you follow that customer's
action throughout every part of system.
Yes.
You need to follow the p- right from
when the customer click the payment,
you need to be able to set your traces
to monitor what goes on at each step.
This enable your engineers to be
able to dive right into it, get
clues whenever an incident occurs,
and fix this incident faster before
a second customer gets to complain.
Then what you need to do next, you
need to create a safe test environment.
Yes.
A safe place to test your
observability against what you
have set Sets your metrics.
Are my metrics actually right
with what alert I have set?
Are my logs actually
getting the right events?
My traces are the right.
You just create a safe test
problem for your platform.
Okay?
This help to s- to see or to monitor
the strength of your observability.
Okay?
And also you need to check whether metric
shows that something is truly wrong.
So once you set this test small test
problem, if your metrics is wrong,
you go back and reconfigure it.
Yes.
So if you set your metrics to trigger
alert when this occurs or to get an
idea of this, and you carry out your
test and your metrics doesn't actually
do what you have set for it to carry
out, then your metrics is wrong.
And then you have to check your logs.
Does it explain why it happened?
What's happened in the event?
Yes.
If it doesn't, then your logs are
actually not carrying out or not
looking in the right direction.
Okay?
So you have to check this type, this
informations to ensure that it is
configured right, it is actually
looking out for the right thing.
Because if you're setting your logs to
look at a different direction, they are
going to give you only information in
that direction, and the information in
that direction might not be important to
actually satisfy your customer's journey.
Okay?
So the next thing is, if any
information is missing, add it.
Yes.
In your collection, you
could add the information.
So if an alert is missing, okay, let's
say in your collection you notice
your collection is not actually giving
you or scraping information in terms
of a particular area, add it up.
Okay, let's say you notice that
your observability alert is actually
giving you alerts for users only
in a particular availability zone,
and you did not configure the
other availability zone, add it up.
Okay?
You can add that up in your observability
alert and in your collection too.
So once this customer journey is
working well You get to repeat
the same process with others.
You get to repeat the same
process with other services.
Okay?
So once you have configured your
system for, let's say now your payment
platform, and you notice that it is
working well, it is sending you the
right alert when something breaks
before it even escalates, then now you
have to move that to other services.
Check all of your services.
Remember, in modern cloud system,
if one service breaks, just a small
of the service will be affected.
If not fixed fast, it's going to spread
and create a more bigger problem.
Okay?
So you have to constantly monitor and set
the right alarm system for your platform.
Okay?
Small, start small, but follow
the journey from beginning to end.
Okay?
So let's bring everything that we've
learned from this section together.
Okay?
So let's bring everything together.
So what is observability?
So observability help
us to do three things.
One, to get to see the problem that
is happening with our application.
Okay?
Two, to get to understand what
actually caused that problem.
Yes.
And three to improve the system
so that the problem is easy
to prevent and fix next time.
Okay?
These are the three core things
that observability help us.
It help us to answer the question of
the what, where, and when, and why.
Okay?
These three things is what
observability help us.
And to be able to answer this
question, there are different types of
information that we need to work with.
One, we need to work with metrics,
which gives us number based on
what is occurring on our platform.
We need to work with logs, which
gives us event datas on what is
actually occurring with our platform.
And then we need to work with traces,
which gives us a step to step of what
is actually going on in our platform.
And together with these three information,
we can set our observability alerts to
trigger for the right customer's journey.
Okay?
And also, we also work with information
such as service level indicat-indicator
and service level objective.
This gives us an idea of what we
should look out for or how our
customers are actually customers'
experience in our platform.
That is what service level
service level indicator gives us.
Okay?
It gives us the customer experience,
the actual customer experience.
Okay?
And now we have a target, which
is our service level objective.
This is a target we give for our platform
to be able to reach in terms of customers'
tax customers' payment transaction,
if that is the case, and all of that.
So putting all of this together, or
putting all of this together and setting
the right configuration, it's going to
make us achieve a successful customer
journey experience and have a very good
platform observability system as well.
Okay?
Dashboards are useful.
Remember, they are very useful, but they
Become more powerful when they are
configured and connected with the right
logs, the right metrics, the right traces,
and to the right customer's journey.
Okay?
They are useful only when they are
connected with the right logs, the right
traces, the right customer's journey, the
right services that we need to monitor.
Okay?
So you don't just need to change
everything in your system at once.
No, you start from bit by bit.
Okay?
You start with one important
customer's journey, one important
service that you need for your
customers to always have access with.
Then you decide what success means,
which data to collect, which data
should my collector actually script what
data should my collector actually get.
Then you determine what is the right data.
Okay?
What is the right
information should I collect?
Then you test your system.
You do a small safety test.
This test help you to say, is
my log configured correctly for
the particular right service?
Are my traces being trace-- Are
my request being traced correctly?
Are the metrics numbers also
showing what is going on, the
right thing that is going on in my
platform?" And improve it over time.
So with time, you can improve all of
this, but you need to start from small.
You don't need to change
your entire platform.
Okay?
And please, observability should be a part
of your system architecture, not after.
Okay?
That is how we get to move beyond
just having dashboard and building
a system that is easy to understand,
a system that gives us clue when an
incident occur, a system that, through
our observability, we can manage the
platform for a better customer journey.
Okay?
So with this being said, I hope you
learned a lot from this section because
it was really interesting why I was
actually why I was actually putting
these details together for you.
And thank you very much for
listening to me, and bye.